{
  "reference_number": "9246",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "As NZ makes .01% of world emissions, while the Govt. may say we can make a difference, we won't make any significant difference at\n all, even if we made no CO2 emissions at all. This is just a \"feel good' issue that is making jobs for people that makes no significant\n\n contribution to the economy of this country. It will be used by some to make money, while not producing anything, but taxing those\n who do."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "How is what our country emits and uses measured? If grass is not in this equation then this equation is flawed and needs to be\n revised."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "As stated before, this is a scheme that people are going to use to make money, but not by doing anything that will reduce the overall\n problem. Forest planting also has limits and issues as well, see the rubbish that is left behind when trees are felled and where that\n\n ends up after severe weather."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "For a start the name Zero Carbon is wrong, as what does it mean? No carbon? How do we do that? Or no CO2? Well we would die\n without it."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Especially the fiscal and competitive considerations any budget targets affect."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But there has to be sufficient consultation with sectors that will be affected."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As farming contributes the single most carbon emissions in NZ ( as many other manufacturers have gone overseas, and we produce\nvery little else) the various farming sectors need to be involved in the process. Research and development are ways NZ could be\n\nworld leaders in the climate change issue. We need to ensure enough money is set aside to enable this to happen."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only if the sectors affected by any budget decisions made, are included in the members of the Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As stated, sectors affected need to have representatives on the Commission. Not just those who are \"well respected\", but those who\nhave been voted on to Boards to represent sectors, eg Fed. Farmers, Dairy Board, Fonterra."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think the task is large enough already, if adaptation is included a different set of skills is probably needed."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Having attended many Regional Council meetings about Emergency Response, the biggest issue facing any Authority trying to deal\nwith aN emergency is OSH, and the fear people will do something that leaves the Authority having to be held accountable. For\nexample, sandbagging riverbanks will not be allowed, as it used to be. It won't be a natural disaster that causes the destruction, it will\n\nbe that people can no longer do things to protect property that they used to do."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, although I thought Regional Councils and District Councils already did this. I am not in favour of more committees being set up if\nthey are only duplicating what is already being done."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please note, I do not give permission for my name, address, email address, or phone number to be published."
    }
  ]
}
